<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>bread on Will Jessop&#39;s Writings</title>
    <link>https://willj.net/tags/bread/</link>
    <description>Recent content in bread on Will Jessop&#39;s Writings</description>
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>will@willj.net (Will Jessop)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>will@willj.net (Will Jessop)</webMaster>
    <copyright>&amp;#169; Will Jessop. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Jan 2021 02:53:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://willj.net/tags/bread/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Simple Sourdough Bread</title>
      <link>https://willj.net/posts/simple-sourdough-bread/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jan 2021 02:53:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>will@willj.net (Will Jessop)</author>
      <guid>https://willj.net/posts/simple-sourdough-bread/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/Hero.jpg#full&#34; alt=&#34;Two sourdough boules&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/Search.jpg#right&#34; alt=&#34;Two sourdough boules&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I make sourdough bread usually at least once a week and sometimes post pictures of the result to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/will_j&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and get asked pretty frequently about my technique. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot written about sourdough bread on the Internet these days, and plenty of YouTube videos on the subject too, but my technique is slightly different to many of them in that it is simple and takes the smallest amount of time possible while still getting great results. I don&amp;rsquo;t have the time to dedicate an entire week to the creation of a loaf of bread, I haven&amp;rsquo;t the patience to softly sing to the dough five times a day, and will not be spending several hours gently cupping the proving basket whispering encouraging thoughts long into the night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have other stuff to do. So, my technique reqires the minimum amount of time. In total a loaf using my technique takes about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 1: about 10 minutes total.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2: 40 minutes to bake + oven pre-heat time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even this seems like a long time, but bear in mind that a lot of this time is spent waiting, for instance the baking and oven warming which is time you can spend doing other important stuff like making lunch, or endlessly doom-scrolling through Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though it&amp;rsquo;s fashionable to add your entire life story as the preamble to any recipe posted on the Web these days, let&amp;rsquo;s draw a line under this introduction and move on to the method. If you&amp;rsquo;re pushed for time to make bread then you&amp;rsquo;re not going to want to read about how a particularly nutty focaccia I ate when I was four set me on the path to posting marginally iterative recipes that I&amp;rsquo;ve made my own &amp;ldquo;with a twist&amp;rdquo; many years later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-starter&#34;&gt;The starter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re going to need a starter. If you&amp;rsquo;ve not got one already, &lt;a href=&#34;https://willj.net/posts/making-a-sourdough-starter/&#34;&gt;head over to my article on making one&lt;/a&gt;, otherwise, read on!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-method&#34;&gt;The Method&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will need:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;250g strong white bread flour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7g salt (about 1 teaspoon for table salt)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;115g water (I just experimented and got to this point, vary the water for the flour you use)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 or 2 teaspoons honey (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;150g starter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recommend starting off with white bread, it seems easier to make, but for wholemeal replace the flour above with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;200g strong white bread flour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;50g wholemeal flour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;30g mixed grains and seeds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;day-1&#34;&gt;Day 1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stir the starter before use in case it has separated at all. If any water has accumulated, stir that in too. Put all the ingredients into a bowl and mix. Once mixed you need to knead it. I use a stand mixer (kitchenaid) on setting 2 for 5 minutes. Hand kneading works too, but it&amp;rsquo;s harder to fiddle with your phone while you do it and you&amp;rsquo;ll need to knead for more like 10 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;youtube-embed&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/U8mvFYiuvqs&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;Me making sourdough&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the bread is kneading, or afterwards if you&amp;rsquo;re doing it by hand, top up the starter with 75g flour and 75g water. If you used more than 150g starter, for instance if you made a larger loaf, alter these quantities respectively. Mix, cover with your cloth and put back in the fridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After kneading do a few stretch and folds (see elsewhere for description), then leave the dough in the bowl covered with a slightly damp tea towel at room temperature for several hours, eight is good to aim for. I often make bread sometime between 11 AM and early evening, then deal with it at about 10PM, but it&amp;rsquo;s pretty robust. You can leave it a longer or shorter time and it should be fine. Don&amp;rsquo;t leave it out overnight, it will develop a dry crust. If you forget and do leave it out overnight though, don&amp;rsquo;t worry about it, you can still use it, it might just not be as good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That evening, take the dough and do some &amp;ldquo;stretches&amp;rdquo;. Take one side of the dough, stretch it over to the other side and attach. rotate the dough, repeat. You should start to feel the dough slightly stiffen or harden. This step doesn&amp;rsquo;t take too long, just get a feel for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, put it in the fridge. I use a banneton, they&amp;rsquo;re about £12 on amazon, but you can probably use some other dish. Flour the inside of it, drop the dough top of the loaf side down in the receptacle, cover, place in the fridge overnight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These steps in total will take about 10 minutes for the initial mix and a few minutes for the step in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;day-2&#34;&gt;Day 2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/finished_bread.jpg&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;h4&gt;A finished loaf.&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day at some point (there&amp;rsquo;s no hard rules about how long to leave it), take the dough out of the fridge, pre-heat the oven to 250°C with a lidded dutch oven inside or similar, lined with baking paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the oven is up to temperature take the dough out of the banneton, score it to help it rise (I find a serrated knife works best for this) then plop into the hot cooking pot. Put the lid on, put it in the oven then turn the oven down to 200 (if you forget this step you will end up with a sourdough rock) and set a timer for 20 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When 20 minutes is up, remove the lid and set the timer for 20 minutes again. When that timer is up it&amp;rsquo;s done, take everything out of the oven and place the bread on a wire cooking rack. Or just balance it on the handle of the cooking pot, this isn&amp;rsquo;t a cooking show, no-one cares.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leave it to mostly cool down before you cut it to prevent it from drying out as the steam escapes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tips-and-examples&#34;&gt;Tips and examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;keeping-it&#34;&gt;Keeping it&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bread is best on the day of baking, but leave it to cool before eating it. If you want to keep it longer than one day I recommend slicing it and freezing it. It makes great toast later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;tips&#34;&gt;Tips&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use good quality strong or very strong white bread flour if you&amp;rsquo;ve got it. It&amp;rsquo;s harder to get it to work with &amp;ldquo;fancy&amp;rdquo;, darker or lower quality flours. I use this: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.shipton-mill.com/bulk-shop/canadian-strong-white.htm&#34;&gt;https://www.shipton-mill.com/bulk-shop/canadian-strong-white.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you use an enamelled dutch oven you may destroy the enamel over time in the hot oven, use a cheaper le crueset knock-off, or one without enamelling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t stress timings too much, a few hours either way is probably fine on any of the steps. It should work around your schedule.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep the starter in the fridge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Different flours need different amounts of water, you just have to experiment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;examples&#34;&gt;Examples&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s some photos of what the end result should look like on my almost never updated instagram:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.instagram.com/willj9000&#34;&gt;https://www.instagram.com/willj9000&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or twitter, for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/will_j/status/1265263352244289537/photo/1&#34;&gt;https://twitter.com/will_j/status/1265263352244289537/photo/1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;if-you-want-to-make-more-than-one-loaf-or-a-larger-loaf&#34;&gt;If you want to make more than one loaf, or a larger loaf&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start to feed the starter with 50/50 flour and water a few days in advance until you have enough starter to take out the amount you will need while still leaving about 150g that you can then feed and put back in the fridge.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Making a Sourdough Starter</title>
      <link>https://willj.net/posts/making-a-sourdough-starter/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jan 2021 02:53:52 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>will@willj.net (Will Jessop)</author>
      <guid>https://willj.net/posts/making-a-sourdough-starter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The absolutely best way of making a starter if you don&amp;rsquo;t already have one is to not make one at all. If you can, ask someone who already has one for a bit of theirs. Most people will be happy to donate a bit, and this is a far shorter way of starting. There&amp;rsquo;s nothing heroic about creating your own, it&amp;rsquo;s mostly just a pain in the butt. If you&amp;rsquo;ve not got one though, here&amp;rsquo;s how make your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Already made your starter and want to make bread? &lt;a href=&#34;https://willj.net/posts/simple-sourdough-bread/&#34;&gt;Head over to the bread recipe!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;things-you-will-need&#34;&gt;Things you will need&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/the_jar.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Sourdough container with a banana propped against it at a jaunty angle&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;h4&gt;My sourdough container, banana for scale.&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make a starter you&amp;rsquo;ll need only four things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Something to keep it in&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it! nothing fancy required. For the most reliable results I recommend using good quality, fresh flour. Don&amp;rsquo;t use the stuff that&amp;rsquo;s a year out of date you found at the back of the cupboard. It might work, but I&amp;rsquo;ve had more luck with good quality fresh flour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The container should be a glass, plastic or non-reactive metal, about one banana in height (see image). It should be very clean and free from dirt or any cleaning product residue. You will also need some sort of cloth to cover it, and an elastic band to keep the cloth in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-method&#34;&gt;The Method&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure to be exact with the measurements, no eyeballing quantities or using weird measurements like &amp;ldquo;cups&amp;rdquo; or anything like that. Also, use a set of digital scales with 1g accuracy if you can, they make baking much easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;full&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/starter_progress.jpg&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;h4&gt;Sourdough progression. Inactive starter on the left, some activity in the middle, the same starter 24 hours later.&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;day-1&#34;&gt;Day 1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mix 50g water (around tap temperature is fine) with 50g flour until you get a smooth paste. Cover with a cloth and leave out at room temperature somewhere it will not get too hot or cold for about 24 hours, so not in the fridge or a sunny windowsill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;day-2&#34;&gt;Day 2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mix 50g flour and 50g water as on day 1 into the existing mixture, cover and leave for another 24 hours&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;day-3-through-7&#34;&gt;Day 3 through 7&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repeat the process from day 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should start to see some bubbling activity on about day 4 and if everything went right you should have a starter after about a week. You should end up with something that smells slightly sour and a bit like yoghurt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might take a little bit longer, it&amp;rsquo;s going to depend on the flour and temperature. If it&amp;rsquo;s not doing anything by about two weeks or it smells like it&amp;rsquo;s gone off then you might need to restart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once it&amp;rsquo;s done, keep the cloth cover on and put it in the fridge until you need it. It will keep about a week without attention in a cold fridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/completed_starter.jpg&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;h4&gt;A working starter.&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/starter_with_lid.jpg&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;h4&gt;Use a cloth lid for your starter to allow it to breath.&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;maintaining-your-starter&#34;&gt;Maintaining your starter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As long as you keep taking some out and then topping it up, the starter should last forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found that my starter keeps best when kept in the fridge as it turns over too fast when any warmer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you use some of the starter, replace what you took with 50/50 water and flour. For example, if you take 150g starter to make a loaf of bread, replace what you took with 75g water and 75g flour. Try to keep the ratios exact. If you bias towards more water for instance each time you&amp;rsquo;re going to end up with wet bread, but bear in mind that over time your starter will suffer from evaporation, so you may need to add a little extra water every once in a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think you might want to make a larger, or multiple loaves in a few days, just add more water and flour over a couple of days until you&amp;rsquo;ve got the amount of starter you will need without taking too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you take the starter out ideally it will be fairly stiff and coagulated, see about 30s into this video (you don&amp;rsquo;t have to stir it for ages, I was just fiddling). Ignore the rest of the video, my technique has changed in some spots, see the &lt;a href=&#34;https://willj.net/posts/simple-sourdough-bread/&#34;&gt;bread recipe&lt;/a&gt; for the updated method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;youtube-embed&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/7OCz-usKlgc&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;Me making sourdough&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The starter should be good to use every day, but if you don&amp;rsquo;t need to make bread for a while it should keep in the fridge for over a week without use. When it&amp;rsquo;s been left for longer than that without being refreshed you can still make bread with it, but it gets harder to get good results. If you leave it too long though it might die and you&amp;rsquo;ll need to start from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your starter has sat for a while then you will find it will become more liquid, this is OK, you can still make bread with it, it just might not be as good. If there is liquid sitting on top of the starter, mix it in. If you pour it out your starter will be unbalanced.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
