<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Abouts on Will Jessop&#39;s Writings</title>
    <link>https://willj.net/about/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Abouts on Will Jessop&#39;s Writings</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>will@willj.net (Will Jessop)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>will@willj.net (Will Jessop)</webMaster>
    <copyright>&amp;#169; Will Jessop. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2023 17:30:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://willj.net/about/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Hire Me</title>
      <link>https://willj.net/about/hire-me-september-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2023 17:30:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>will@willj.net (Will Jessop)</author>
      <guid>https://willj.net/about/hire-me-september-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi, I am Will Jessop, an extensively experienced programmer, sysadmin and technical leader. As a consultant and contractor I focus on:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ruby on Rails performance and application scaling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Application architecture planning and implementation for robustness and scale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ruby on Rails upgrades
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Doing the ugprades themselves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Planning and implementing processes for&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organisational stuff somehow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am also open to longer term senior technical leadership roles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;experience&#34;&gt;Experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;impactive-boston-usa---cto&#34;&gt;Impactive (Boston, USA) - CTO&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I joined Impactive (then Outvote) the organisation was struggling with a number of issues. The most immediate concern was that they had won the contract to run all voter outreach and communication for the Biden campaign in the 2020 presidential election, a contract that would see orders of magnitude more traffic than they got day to day, but the application was struggling under the existing load. There was a serious time-pressure to scale and re-architect where possible to meet the deadline of voter outreach starting before the election. I quickly got to work identifying critical paths within the application, ading performance monitoring implementing fixes for a large number of issues. In the end Impactive handled the election traffic successfully for all clients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identified all critical paths within the application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Added performance montoring tools and introduced these to the team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Significantly optimised a large amount of database usage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Re-architected a number of systems to be much more scalable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, the development organisation itself was in trouble. There was no clear organisation, morale was low and key employees were burnt out and leaving. Projects routinely ran over with little to no oversight, understaning of requirements was minimal leading to discrepancies between the desired outcome of projects and what was built, communication was mostly on-way down the pipeline so there was no feedback on pace of development&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Impactive I completely overhauled the product pipeline from planning through to deploy, introducing a completely new process structure and a development cycle. I reduced employee turnover, increased employee happiness, and increased the overall quality of the codebase and application while increasing project throughput.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduced a new eight week development cycle&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;details …&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weekly planning meetings between leaders to check on progress, re-assess priorities, adjusting the map where necessary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meetings to plan the cycle. All project stakeholders inc. CEO and COO would get together to discuss priorities  fotr the organisation for the upcoming cycle&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cycle kick-off, re-inforced the mission, build a sense of a shared goal and belonging&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Per-team Project kick-off meetings with projects stakeholders to increase understanding of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Increased quality, a sense of pride and ownership in work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Projects were assigned to engineers with little regard for the workload they currently had&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding of what was expected in projects was hazy leading to extra work due to implementing the wrong thing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too many meetings/interruptions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unclear prioroties&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quality&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Changing the culture of quality was hard, inertia due to people being used to having to push stuff fast.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;quality
scaling
organisation, tracking work, overruns
handover meetings, check ins, project cycle kickoffs with stakeholders&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also significantly scaled and optimised the Rails application and Postgres to handle the 2020 US election traffic (we handled the outreach communications for the Biden campaign) and for the democrats during the midterm elections in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Database performance
Ruby on Rails performance
Application tuning (env vars etc)
organisation stuff&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tanda
Database performance
education
Procore
imlementing plans etc.
Stuart
Doing the upgrade&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previous&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;37signals/Basecamp
Engineyard&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rails scaling, performance, and upgrade and Postgres scaling and performance contracting/consultancy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are my core technical skills and I am more productive when I stick to these areas. A lot of the short to medium term contracts I have done have been in these areas. Here&amp;rsquo;s some relatively recent&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Procore, Implementing and managing the upgrade process from Rails 4.2 through 5.1. This was a huge codebase with nearly 2000 HTTP endpoints&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stuart, same as Procore. Seamless upgrade with no customer incidents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impactive, significant database, query and code optimisations, and architectural planning and implementation to allow them to scale to some huge traffic levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tanda, query optimisation and database tuning to massively reduce database iOPS and query performance in general.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get started simply email me at &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:will@willj.net?subject=Interested%20in%20hiring%20you&#34;&gt;will@willj.net&lt;/a&gt;. I usually kick things off by setting up a 45 minute call to go through requirements and to make sure that I can help you before sending a contract.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;rates-and-billing&#34;&gt;Rates and Billing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of this is negotiable, but the basics of hiring me are as follows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My current basic rate is $300 USD/hour or local equivalent based on the exchange rate at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For longer term and retained contracts I will discount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can bill in most currencies and to most countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I invoice bi-weekly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are in the UK or EU there will be VAT added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;miscellanea&#34;&gt;Miscellanea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Working with companies in non-UK timezones is not a problem&lt;/strong&gt;, I have worked extensively with US companies coast to coast, Europe, and also New Zealand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I primarily work remotely, however:-
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where desired I will travel to meet and work with your team for short to medium periods, expenses such as travel and accomodation will be covered by you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am happy to travel internationally, I prefer BA business class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
